Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/szeeshanrizvi (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Matlab

Simulations

Simulink

Languages

Urdu (Native or Bilingual)
English (Professional Working)

Publications

Data-driven modeling and predictive control of combustion phasing for RCCI engines

State-space LPV model identification using kernelized machine learning

Linear parameter-varying approach for modeling rapid thermal processes

A kernel-based PCA approach to model reduction of linear parameter-varying systems

Parameter set-mapping using kernelbased PCA for linear parametervarying systems

Patents

Method for Hammerstein modeling of steam generator plant

Reduced complexity auto-tuning process controller system and method

Robust Controller For Nonlinear MIMO Systems

Zeeshan Rizvi, Ph.D.

Sr. Data Scientist at Corning Inc.

Steuben County, New York, United States

Summary

Data Scientist with a Ph.D. in Controls, Modeling, and Optimization. Involved in developing and deploying data-driven solutions for manufacturing. Core focus is on predictive modeling and analytics for equipment reliability improvement, data-driven process monitoring, and process improvement using model-based advanced controls. Six Sigma Green Belt certified.

Experienced in development using: Python, Matlab, OpenCV, DataBricks, PySpark, SQL, Gitlab, Power BI, Latex.

Experience

Corning Incorporated 6 years 4 months

Sr. Data Scientist, Projects Lead May 2022 - Present (1 year)

Corning, New York, United States

Developing and deploying predictive modeling and data-driven solutions for optimizing manufacturing reliability and processes.

Sr. Process Controls Engineer/Scientist July 2020 - May 2022 (1 year 11 months) Corning, New York

Advanced process controls and process monitoring solutions using multivariate data analytics, machine learning, and model-based control design methods like Model Predictive Control.

Adv. Process Controls Engineer/Scientist January 2017 - July 2020 (3 years 7 months) Corning, New York

The University of Georgia
Graduate Research Assistant
January 2013 - January 2017 (4 years 1 month)

Athens, Georgia

Doctoral research: Developing ML models, system identification, and control design of nonlinear industrial processes under the framework of Linear Parameter-Varying (LPV) models.

Air Products
R&D Intern
February 2016 - May 2016 (4 months)

Allentown, Pennsylvania

Analytics and optimization of world's largest Hydrogen pipeline project.

Statistical analysis of process and business data, building regression and timeseries models to predict gas and power pricing.

King Fahd University of Petroleum & Minerals - KFUPM Lecturer March 2009 - December 2012 (3 years 10 months)

Dhahran, Saudi Arabia

Taught undergraduate EE courses. Published peer-reviewed articles. Was awarded 3 patents by USPTO.

Siemens Control & Instrumentation Engineer July 2008 - September 2008 (3 months)

Al-Khobar, Saudi Arabia

Education

The University of Georgia

Doctor of Philosophy (PhD), Electrical Engineering (2013 - 2017)

King Fahd University of Petroleum & Minerals

Master of Science (MS), Electrical and Electronics Engineering (2006 - 2008)

NED University of Engineering and Technology Bachelor of Engineering (BE), Electrical and Electronics Engineering · (2002 - 2006)